James Garfield the 20th president of the
United States gave this proof of the
Pythagorean theorem start with a right
triangle with legs of length A and B and
hypotenuse of length C place a rotated
copy so that complimentary angles fit
together creating a right isoceles
triangle with leg length C the area of
the newly created triangle is 12 c^ 2
and the area of the original right
triangle is 12 a * B so the area
enclosed in this trapezoid diagram is
c^2 + a * B on the other hand using the
formula for the area of a trapezoid we
see that the is 12 a + b * A + B and
this simplifies to 1 12 * the quantity a
2 + 2 a + b^ 2 because these two
quantities measure the same area we
conclude that c^2 + a = A2 + 2 A + B ^2
applying some Elementary algebra shows
us that c^2 equal A2 + b^2 When A and B
are the legs of a right triangle with
hypotenuse C this is Garfield's
trapezoid proof of the right triangle
theorem